Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we try to
answer the question
do the benefits of Ozempic
outweigh the risks?
Even the drug manufacturers
of Ozempic
and similar weight-loss drugs
cop to the long list
of potentially serious
side effects.
The absolute risks, though,
for serious issues
like pancreatitis,
thyroid cancer,
bowel obstruction,
were all about 1% or less
per year
of using GLP-1-type drugs.
Of course, when millions
of people are on these drugs,
even relatively rare
side effects
will occur
in a large number of people.
But you know what else
can have serious side effects?
Obesity.
In fact, one potential
side effect of GLP-1 drugs
is that they could be
too effective,
risking excessive weight loss.
Any discussion
of risks versus benefits
has to take any benefits
of the weight loss itself
into account.
Excess body fat
is a major risk factor
for metabolic diseases,
involving nearly
every organ in our body,
such as Type II diabetes,
heart disease, stroke,
dementia, liver disease,
sleep apnea,
osteoarthritis, infertility,
several cancers,
including breast cancer
and colon cancer,
even psychiatric disorders.
Consider
the overall health outcomes
of those undergoing
bariatric surgery,
which is not exactly
a benign procedure.
In the United States,
for instance,
hundreds of thousands
go under the knife
to lose weight.
Roux-en-Y gastric bypass
is one of
the most popular techniques
and is thought to be
the "gold standard" method
given its safety record,
with a mortality rate
less 0.5%.
Wait, they’re bragging
about not killing
more than 1 in 200 people
in the operating room?
The surgery
is a major rearrangement
of your digestive tract,
but it can induce
a long-term weight loss
of about 25%,
which is similar
to some of the best results
of the new GLP-1 drugs.
So, if you only care
about living longer,
might the benefits
of weight loss
outweigh the risks of dying
on the operating table?
Based on a meta-analysis
of millions of patients,
only about 1 in 1,250 people
appear to be killed
directly by the surgery,
and since the ones
who don’t lose their lives
tend to lose so much weight,
bariatric surgery
has been associated
with a six-year longer lifespan.
So, on average,
choosing to go under the knife
may significantly
extend your life,
even after taking into account
the risk
of the operation itself
killing you.
But, of course, there’s also
the risk of complications.
Approximately 1 in 4
bariatric surgery patients
experience adverse effects
in the five years
following surgery,
and for 1 in 50,
it’s so bad
that they have to go back
onto the operating table
for further surgery.
That’s one advantage
of the drug approach.
If you experience
some serious side effect,
it may go away
when you stop taking the drug,
whereas if you’ve already
had your stomach cut out,
or your intestines rearranged,
there may be less
that can be done about it.
Here’s a list
of the pros and cons.
Researchers looked at
the impact of bariatric surgery
on more than five dozen
health outcomes.
And although people
who underwent surgery
may be more likely
to kill themselves,
break bones,
and suffer acid reflux,
they also appear
to get less diabetes,
high blood pressure,
and high cholesterol,
and less cancer
and cardiovascular disease.
Here’s how it breaks down.
Just looking at
the statistically
significant associations,
we can see that those
who’ve had bariatric surgery
had a lower risk of dying
from all causes put together,
as well as dying
specifically from diabetes,
cancer,
and cardiovascular disease,
but they are
at an increased risk
of taking their own lives.
In terms of metabolic outcomes,
lower risks of getting diabetes,
high blood pressure
and high cholesterol.
Lower risks of continuing
to have diabetes,
high blood pressure,
and cholesterol,
and a lower risk
of diabetic complications.
In terms of getting cancer,
there’s a lower risk
of developing
different types of cancer
and getting
any kind of cancer at all.
A lower risk of all
the cardiovascular diseases
the researchers looked at,
and most
of the digestive diseases
except for reflux
with sleeve gastrectomy,
and higher or lower risk
of kidney stones
depending on procedure,
but it generally seems
to be kidney protective.
For women’s health,
after bariatric surgery,
they had less
urinary incontinence
and polycystic ovary syndrome,
and fewer problems
during pregnancy,
though the outcomes
for infants are mixed,
with more preterm
birth and death.
And finally,
less anxiety and depression,
though more self-harm,
and a lower risk
of being hospitalized
and dying from COVID.
So, generally, the benefits
far outweigh the risks,
but, really, that says less
about the benefits of surgery
and more about the risks
of excess body fat.
With the GLP-1 drugs,
we see
largely similar improvements
in things like
blood sugar control,
blood pressure,
and cholesterol,
and maybe even
similar clinical outcomes,
like the risk of dying.
If that were the case,
then for most people
with obesity,
like with the bariatric surgery,
the benefits of these new drugs
would be expected
to far exceed the risks.
Yes, there are still issues
with the cost
of these potentially
life-long medications,
and lack of knowledge
of their long-term side effects,
and this, of course,
assumes you’re taking
the actual drug.
Shortages of these pills
have led patients
to compounding pharmacies
that offer versions of the drugs
that have not been approved
by the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration,
which in the past has led
to serious safety issues,
like an epidemic
of fungal meningitis
caused by moldy bottles of drugs
from compounding pharmacies.
751 patients
were ultimately affected,
and more than 60 patients died.
But at least
compounding pharmacies
have some kind of regulation.
Nowadays,
people can get injected
with God knows what
at so-called medical spas
that may not be under
any form of regulation.
People don’t seem
to be paying much attention
to these FDA warnings.
As an article
in Rolling Stone put it,
"The FDA warned Ozempic users,"
but, "They don’t give a ..."
Yes, these drugs
can improve risk factors,
but the risk-benefit analysis
really depends on
these clinical disease outcomes.
Do people really live longer
on these drugs?
Have less heart attacks?
"Thinner is better,"
is the conventional wisdom
when it comes
to minimizing the risk
of cardiovascular events
like heart attacks and strokes,
but there have been cases
where weight loss medications
actually led to increased
cardiovascular risk
despite significant
reductions in body fat.
So, we can’t just assume
drug-induced weight loss
will help.
Now, if it’s true
that GLP-1 drugs, like Ozempic,
reduce cardiovascular events,
which are some
of our leading causes of death,
then that benefit
would significantly overwhelm
the risk of almost any amount
of thyroid cancer
these drugs may cause.
Let’s look at the data.
Some major trials have found
that among high-risk
individuals with diabetes,
risk of cardiovascular events
were significantly lower
among those
randomized to Ozempic
compared to placebo injections,
but other trials did not.
Interesting how
the lack of benefit was spun
by saying, "Hey,
it’s not inferior to placebo."
But that was the main concern,
that Ozempic, like some
other weight loss drugs,
could actually increase
cardiovascular disease.
So, it was considered a relief
that it had no effect.
Enough evidence
of benefit accrued, though,
that Ozempic
and another GLP-1 drug
were approved
for cardiovascular protection
among individuals
with Type II diabetes.
Remember, these were
originally prescribed
as diabetes drugs.
So, maybe users reduced
their cardiovascular risk
just by lowering
their blood sugars
rather than
by lowering their weight.
What we want to know is this.
What is the effect of Ozempic
on cardiovascular outcomes
in obesity
for people without diabetes?
And, in patients
who have preexisting
cardiovascular disease,
and are overweight or obese,
but do not have diabetes,
those randomized
to weight loss doses of Ozempic
had an overall lower rate
of either having
a cardiovascular event,
like a heart attack or stroke,
or dying from it,
compared to placebo.
That’s exciting,
but we have to highlight
another caveat, though.
The researchers
just looked at
those with preexisting
cardiovascular disease.
That is an important
limitation of these findings.
The effects of these
weight-loss drugs
on the prevention
of cardiovascular events
in those without diagnosed
atherosclerotic disease
have not yet been determined.
Still, a lot
of overweight people
have a history of heart attack,
stroke,
or peripheral vascular disease.
So, how big is the benefit?
Over a period of a few years,
8% of people
with cardiovascular disease
suffered another event
on the placebo,
but only 6.5%
suffered a subsequent event
on the drug.
Going from 8 to 6.5
is a 20% drop.
Unfortunately,
many news stories focused on
that 20% relative risk reduction
rather than on
the absolute risk reduction
of 1.5%.
Yes, 8 to 6.5 is a 20% drop,
but, at the same time,
you’re really only reducing
your absolute risk by 1.5%.
In other words,
you’d have to treat
67 people with the drug
for a few years
to prevent one heart attack
or stroke
or cardiovascular death.
That may not sound like much
on an individual scale.
I mean, what are the odds
you’re going to be
that 1 in 67th person?
But on a population scale,
it’s huge.
In fact, it’s right up there
with cholesterol-lowering
statin drugs,
which have
an absolute risk reduction
in the same 1.5% ballpark.
So, indeed, in March 2024,
the Food and Drug Administration
approved high-dose Ozempic
for use beyond just weight loss
but also for reducing
cardiovascular risk
in those with
prior cardiovascular disease.
So, how do the benefits
and harms stack up?
In the summer of 2024,
the first quantitative
benefit-harm balance analysis
was published.
The researchers concluded
that for those achieving
a 10% weight loss,
there’s more than a 90% chance
the benefits outweigh the harms,
though the opposite was found
for only a 5% weight loss.
Here’s how they broke it down.
If 1,000 people
go on these GLP-1 drugs,
375 would be expected to lose
at least 10%
of their body weight
with all the ancillary benefits
that would bring.
On the other side
of the equation,
41 people would suffer
from abdominal pain,
57 from hair loss,
8 from gallstones,
118 from constipation,
100 from diarrhea,
22 from dizziness,
84 from an upset stomach,
46 from excessive burping,
39 from fatigue,
51 from excessive farting,
13 from headaches,
17 from low blood sugars,
4 from reactions
at the injection site.
221 would suffer from nausea,
4 from pancreatitis,
43 from upper abdominal pain,
and 110 from vomiting.
Now, of course, the net benefit
versus harm calculation
would be highly dependent on
different people’s willingness
to accept different harms.
Like a bald guy
isn’t going to be concerned
about hair loss, for example.
And this also
doesn’t take into account
the fact that
the benefits peter out.
Weight loss stalls after a year,
but the harms may continue.
So, once
you’ve already plateaued
and stop losing weight,
do you keep taking it
even though you get
no further weight-loss benefit
but the potential for harm
continues to accumulate?
We really don’t know about
the long-term harms or benefits
because some of these drugs
and dosing schedules are so new,
especially now that the American
Academy of Pediatrics
has suggested
offering these drugs
for teens and tweens
as young as age 12.
These drugs work
by acting on the brain,
so, who knows what effect
this could have
on childhood development
and beyond,
if they end up taking them
for the rest of their lives.
In the end,
this story is familiar.
A new class
of antidiabetic agents
is rushed to market
and widely promoted
in the absence
of any evidence
of long-term
beneficial outcomes.
Evidence of harms accumulate,
but it’s vigorously denied
or discounted.
The manufacturers are expected,
quite unrealistically,
to monitor the safety
of their own products.
We should be thankful
that those responsible
for aircraft safety
do not operate
under the same assumption.
Although we now
do have evidence
of at least near-term benefit
over a few years,
we cannot assume
long-term safety
until it has been demonstrated.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.